<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="94">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 08, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01216176</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20080325</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>SCCC-2008002</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01216176</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pharmacokinetic and Randomized Trial of Neoadjuvant Treatment With Anastrozole Plus AZDO530 in Postmenopausal Patients With Hormone Receptor Positive Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Pharmacokinetic and Randomized Phase II Trial of Neoadjuvant Treatment With Anastrozole Plus AZDO530 in Postmenopausal Patients With Hormone Receptor Positive Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Joyce Marie Slingerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose to conduct a Phase I/randomized Phase II study design in order to
      test the tolerability and efficacy or AZD0530 when used together with anastrozole in therapy
      of ER+ and/or PR+ postmenopausal breast cancer. The Phase I pharmacokinetic (PK) cohort of
      the study (cohort A) was conducted in postmenopausal women with metastatic breast cancer in
      2008-2009 and showed initial safety,tolerability and good bioavailability of this drug
      combination and determined the dose for use in the ongoing Phase II trial. In the randomized
      Phase II cohort of the study (cohort B), postmenopausal women with newly diagnosed,
      previously untreated  ER+, HER2 negative breast cancer that is at least 2 cm or more in
      diameter by clinical exam or radiology will be randomized to either neoadjuvant treatment
      with anastrozole plus placebo, or anastrozole in combination with AZD0530. The Phase II
      cohort will permit extended assays of tolerability, initial estimates of efficacy, and the
      investigation of molecular (protein and RNA expression profiles) and cellular assays
      (measures of TICs) as predictors of drug efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I Cohort A: To determine if a well tolerated dose of AZD0530 can be used in combination with anastrozole for postmenopausal women with ER+/PR+ metastatic breast cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1: Days 1 - 28</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Cohort B: Compare treatment groups (AZD0530 + Anastrozole versus Anastrozole alone with respect to clinical response.</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each 28 day cycle, for a total of 6 cycles</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Clinical response is defined as percentage change/reduction in tumor size as measured by manual and/or caliper measurement of tumor volume at diagnosis and on completion of neoadjuvant treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I - Cohort A: To test the effects of giving AZD0530 and Anastrozole together on pharmacokinetics of both drugs</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1: 0 hrs, 6 hrs, 12 hrs, 24hrs, 48 hrs, 72 hrs, 7 days, 14 days, 21 days after first dose of AZD0530</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Blood draws at protocol-specified timepoints to determine pharmacokinetics of ADZ0530 and Anastrozole.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Cohort B: Evaluation of pathologic complete response (pCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of neoadjuvant therapy and after definitive surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of tumor specimen in patients undergoing mastectomy or breast-conserving procedure to determine response (pCR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Cohort B: Clinical Benefit (complete (CR), or partial (PR) responses or stable disease (SD))</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of neoadjuvant therapy</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Measured by physician measurement of tumor size and by MRI measurements of tumor volume at diagnosis and prior to surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Cohort B: Qualitative and Quantitative Toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 treatment cycles and up to 2 months after surgery or after therapy/withdrawal</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Patients who have tumor removal breast surgery after neoadjuvant therapy will be assessed  up to 2 months after surgery. In the event the tumor is not-operable, toxicity will evaluated for the last time up to 2 months after discontinuing therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Cohort B: To identify molecular/biologic correlates as indicators of treatment response</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of neoadjuvant therapy and after definitive surgery</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluation of biomarkers including Ki67 and p27, EGFR, Her2, Src, Akt and MAPK Levels, localization and phosphorylation as assayed by immunohistochemistry. Other biomarkers may be considered pending initial IHC results.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II cohort B: Evaluation of clinical response defined as percentage change/reduction in tumor size by comparison of serial MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline , 10 weeks from study start date and pre-operative</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MRI will be used to compare tumor size prior to drug therapy , at 10 weeks on study and prior to surgery on completion of study medication</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 - Cohort A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrozole + AZ0530]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrazole + Placebo]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anastrozole</intervention_name>
    <description>1 mg orally per day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 - Cohort A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrozole + AZ0530]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrazole + Placebo]</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ADZ0530</intervention_name>
    <description>175 mg orally per day or as otherwise specified in protocol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 - Cohort A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrozole + AZ0530]</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>175 mg orally per day or as otherwise specified in protocol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrazole + Placebo]</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacokinetic studies</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood draws at protocol-specified timepoints to determine pharmacokinetics of ADZ0530 and Anastrozole.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 - Cohort A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrozole + AZ0530]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrazole + Placebo]</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PK</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Definitive Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Breast Conserving Lumpectomy or Mastectomy - after completion of neoadjuvant therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrozole + AZ0530]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrazole + Placebo]</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Core Biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Core Biopsy at Baseline, snap frozen, paraffin-embedded</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrozole + AZ0530]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrazole + Placebo]</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumor Tissue Collection for Genetic and Molecular Studies</intervention_name>
    <description>Recovery of tumor tissue at the time of definitive surgery - snap frozen, for correlative genetic and molecular studies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrozole + AZ0530]</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 - Cohort B [Anastrazole + Placebo]</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria - Phase 1 (Cohort A):

          -  Female patient &gt; 18 years

          -  Patient must be postmenopausal, verified by 1 of the following:

               -  Bilateral surgical oophorectomy

               -  No spontaneous menses &gt; 1 year

               -  No menses for &lt; 1 year with FSH and estradiol levels in postmenopausal range

          -  Postmenopausal women with primary invasive breast cancer, histologically confirmed by
             core needle (or incisional biopsy), whose tumors are estrogen (ER) and/or
             progesterone (PgR) positive. Estrogen- and/or progesterone-receptor positive disease
             based on 10% or more nuclear staining of the invasive component of the tumor

          -  Stage IV disease (as defined by the AJCC Staging Manual, 6th Edition, 2002); or
             locally relapsed, unresectable disease

          -  Measurable or evaluable disease according to RECIST criteria (see appendix VII)

          -  Both HER2-positive and HER2-negative disease (as defined by IHC or by fluorescence in
             situ hybridization [FISH]). HER2+ must have had prior treatment with trastuzumab
             and/or lapatinib.

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2 (see appendix VI)

          -  Patients are suitable candidates for treatment with anastrozole (patients may have
             had any prior endocrine therapy or prior chemotherapy for treatment of their disease,
             either as adjuvant therapy, or as treatment for advanced disease). There is no
             restriction on the number of prior regimens in the phase I cohort A.

          -  Patient is accessible and willing to comply with treatment and follow-up

          -  Patient is willing to provide written informed consent prior to the performance of
             any study-related procedures

          -  Required laboratory values

               -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1.5 x 109/L

               -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9.0 g/dL

               -  Platelet count &gt; 100 x 109/L

               -  Creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dL

               -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.0 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Alkaline phosphatase and AST/ALT within protocol parameters. In determining
                  eligibility, the more abnormal of the two values (AST or ALT) should be used.

        Inclusion Criteria - Phase 2 (Cohort B):

          -  Female patient &gt; 18 years

          -  Patient must be postmenopausal, verified by 1 of the following:

               -  Bilateral surgical oophorectomy

               -  No spontaneous menses &gt; 1 year

               -  No menses for &lt; 1 year with FSH and estradiol levels in postmenopausal range

          -  Postmenopausal women with primary invasive breast cancer, histologically confirmed by
             core needle (or incisional biopsy), whose tumors are estrogen (ER) and/or
             progesterone (PgR) positive. Estrogen- and/or progesterone-receptor positive disease
             based on 10% or more nuclear staining of the invasive component of the tumor.
             Patients may have bilateral or multifocal invasive breast cancers. The patient may
             have concurrent DCIS in either breast but the DCIS will not be measured as part of
             the study endpoints.

          -  Tumor size &gt; or = 2 cm

          -  Tumor measurable either by clinical examination, mammography, MRI, or ultrasound

          -  HER2-negative disease (as defined by fluorescence in situ hybridization [FISH] or by
             IHC)

          -  ECOG performance status 0-1 (see Appendix VI)

          -  No prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or endocrine therapy for the new presenting
             invasive breast cancer.

          -  Patient is accessible and willing to comply with treatment and follow-up

          -  Patient is willing to provide written informed consent prior to the performance of
             any study-related procedures

          -  Required laboratory values

               -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1.5 x 109/L

               -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9.0 g/dL

               -  Platelet count &gt; 70 x 109/L

               -  Creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dL

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Alkaline phosphatase and AST/ALT &lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

        Exclusion Criteria - Phase 1 (Cohort A):

          -  Concurrent therapy with any other non-protocol anti-cancer therapy.

               -  Any agent with estrogenic or putatively estrogenic properties, including herbal
                  preparations, must be stopped at least one week prior to registration.

               -  Ongoing, chronic administration of bisphosphonate therapy is allowed so long as
                  such treatment was ongoing at the time of study entry.

          -  Current therapy with hormone replacement therapy, or any hormonal agent such as
             raloxifene, tamoxifen, or other selective estrogen receptor modulators (agents must
             be stopped prior to randomization)

          -  Presence of neuropathy &gt; grade 2 (NCI-CTC version 3.0) at baseline

          -  History of any other malignancy within the past 5 years, with the exception of
             non-melanoma skin cancer or carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease (e.g., hypertension [BP &gt; 150/100],
             history of myocardial infarction or stroke within 6 months, unstable angina), New
             York Heart Association (NYHA) Grade II or greater congestive heart failure, or
             serious cardiac arrhythmia requiring medication

          -  Active, uncontrolled infection requiring parenteral antimicrobials

          -  The presence of any other medical or psychiatric disorder that, in the opinion of the
             treating physician, would contraindicate the use of the drugs in this protocol or
             place the subject at undue risk for treatment complications

          -  A history of a severe hypersensitivity reaction to anastrozole, or AZD0530 or their
             excipients

          -  Evidence of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy.

          -  Resting EKG with measurable QTc interval of &gt;480msec at 2 or more time points within
             a 24 hr period.

          -  Since AZD0530 is a substrate and inhibitor of CYP3A4,patients requiring medication
             with drugs should be excluded from study.

          -  Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic conditions (e.g. Severe hepatic
             impairment, interstitial lung disease [bilateral, diffuse, parenchymal lung disease])
             or current unstable or uncompensated respiratory or cardiac conditions which make it
             undesirable for the patient to participate in the study or which could jeopardize
             compliance with the protocol

          -  Evidence of underlying pulmonary dysfunction as evidenced by oxygen saturation &lt;90%
             by pulse oximetry, interstitial pulmonary infiltrates on high resolution CT scan
             prior to study entry and/or symptomatic pulmonary (pleural or parenchymal)
             metastasis.

        Exclusion Criteria - Phase 2 (Cohort B):

          -  Prior chemotherapy, endocrine therapy or radiotherapy for the presenting breast
             cancer.  Prior incidence and treatment of contralateral invasive or non-invasive
             breast cancer is not an exclusion criterion.

          -  Inflammatory breast cancer, clinically defined as the presence of erythema or
             induration involving one-third or more of the breast, or pathologically defined as
             dermal lymphatic invasion

          -  Prior excisional biopsy or complete resection of the primary invasive tumor (prior
             sentinel node biopsy allowed)

          -  Prior ipsilateral radiation therapy for invasive or non-invasive breast cancer

          -  Distant metastasis - Isolated ipsilateral supraclavicular node involvement and/or
             direct invasion of the primary tumor into skin is allowed

          -  Concurrent therapy with any other non-protocol anti-cancer therapy Any agent with
             estrogenic or putatively estrogenic properties, including herbal preparations, must
             be stopped at least one week prior to registration

          -  Current therapy with hormone replacement therapy, or any hormonal agent such as
             raloxifene, tamoxifen, or other selective estrogen receptor modulators (agents must
             be stopped for one week prior to randomization)

          -  Presence of neuropathy &gt; grade 2 (NCI-CTC AE version 3.0) at baseline

          -  History of any other malignancy within the past 5 years, with the exception of
             non-melanoma skin cancer or carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease (e.g., history of myocardial infarction
             or stroke within 6 months, unstable angina), New York Heart Association (NYHA) Grade
             II or greater congestive heart failure, or serious cardiac arrhythmia requiring
             medication

          -  Active, uncontrolled infection requiring parenteral antimicrobials

          -  The presence of any other medical or psychiatric disorder that, in the opinion of the
             treating physician, would contraindicate the use of the drugs in this protocol or
             place the subject at undue risk for treatment complications

          -  A history of a severe hypersensitivity reaction to anastrozole, or AZD0530 or their
             excipients

          -  Evidence of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy

          -  Resting EKG with measurable QTc interval of &gt;480msec at 2 or more time points within
             a 24 hr period.

          -  AZD0530 is a substrate and inhibitor of CYP3A4. Since concurrent administration of
             AZD0530 with other CYP3A4 substrates has been shown to be well tolerated,
             continuation or initiation of medically indicated drugs that are substrates of CYP3A4
             is permitted at MD discretion. Drugs listed in Appendix XI that are known to strongly
             induce or inhibit CYP3A4 activity should be discontinued prior to study entry and
             should not be initiated during protocol treatment.

          -  Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic conditions (eg. Severe hepatic
             impairment, interstitial lung disease [bilateral, diffuse, parenchymal lung disease])
             or current unstable or uncompensated respiratory or cardiac conditions which make it
             undesirable for the patient to participate in the study or which could jeopardize
             compliance with the protocol

          -  Evidence of underlying pulmonary dysfunction as evidenced by oxygen saturation &lt;90%
             by pulse oximetry, interstitial pulmonary infiltrates on high resolution CT scan
             prior to study entry and/or symptomatic pulmonary (pleural or parenchymal) disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joyce Slingerland, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</last_name>
    <phone>866-574-5124</phone>
    <email>sylvester@emergingmed.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark D Pegram, MD</last_name>
      <phone>650-723-5801</phone>
      <email>mpegram@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Karen Lau, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>650-723-0658</phone>
      <email>kkwlau@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark D Pegram, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>University of Miami Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-574-5124</phone>
      <email>sylvester@emergingmed.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joyce Slingerland, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Judith Hurley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen Richman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Vogel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Reshma Mahtani, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc Lippman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mohammed Jahanzeb, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>June 24, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 5, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joyce Marie Slingerland</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Postmenopausal</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Phase I ONLY</keyword>
  <keyword>AZD0530</keyword>
  <keyword>Anastrozole</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase I for metastatic disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase II for newly diagnosed breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <keyword>PK</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormone Receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Estrogen Receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Progesterone Receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>ER+</keyword>
  <keyword>PR+</keyword>
  <keyword>HER negative</keyword>
  <keyword>Aromatase Inhibitors</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anastrozole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
