<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="69">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 08, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01775072</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-245</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01775072</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tumor Genomic Profiling in Patients Evaluated for Targeted Cancer Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tumor Genomic Profiling in Patients Evaluated for Targeted Cancer Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether certain genes in cancer may be abnormal.
      When a gene is abnormal this is called a mutation. Most mutations in cancer cells are not
      inherited (passed down from parents) but happen after birth in the cancer itself. Most
      cancers have many mutations. Some of these mutations are important for the cancer cells to
      survive while others are not. The goal of this study is test cancer for certain mutations
      using leftover tumor tissue from a previous surgery or biopsy. Participants will also be
      asked to provide a tube of blood cheek (also known as a buccal) swab,  or a saliva sample
      that contains normal genes for comparison.

      The purpose of Part B of this study is to:

      Understand how genetic changes in tumor effect the chance of responding to experimental
      cancer treatment. Understand how the genes in the tumor change overtime in response to
      targeted cancer treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>frequency of &quot;actionable&quot; oncogenic mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>&quot;Actionable&quot; mutations will be defined as either 1) a mutation shown to predict for sensitivity or resistance to a drug FDA approved for use in another cancer indication or 2) a mutation which predicts for sensitivity or resistance in preclinical models to an investigational class of drugs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the impact of molecular profiling results performed in the CLIA-setting on the treatment of patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Bioinformatics Core will assist in interpreting data generated by next-generation sequencing techniques such as WES and WGS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>interrogate the mechanisms</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>underlying response and resistance (de-novo and acquired) to targeted therapy. The research assay(s) used to accomplish this will vary based on the clinical setting and tissue available and may include Sanger, Sequenom, MiSeq, exon-capture (ie: IMPACT), whole exome, and whole genome sequencing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To explore the genetic mechanisms of tumorigenesis</measure>
    <time_frame>2</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>in a subset of specimens with no identifiable culpritic genomic alterations on highly-multiplexed next-generation sequencing (i.e.: IMPACT testing) by using even more comprehensive investigational profiling techniques such as whole exome sequencing, whole genome sequencing or RNA sequencing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Hematologic Cancers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pts with solid tumors</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients must have solid or hematologic cancer. for treatment on a . Patients must have undergone pathologic confirmation of their tumor at MSKCC and have either: 1) archival tissue available for analysis, 2) have fresh tissue collection planned as routine standard of care biopsy  or part of a research biopsy under another clinical trial(or peripheral blood / bone marrow collection in the case of hematologic cancers) outside of the context of this protocol, or 3)archival tissue .available at an outside facility. For prospective genotyping tissue specimens from the primary site, a metastasis or recurrence will be used based upon the availability and quality of tissue.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>molecular profiling of tumors</intervention_name>
    <description>Part A is the molecular profiling of tumors. No new tumor biopsies will be performed in the context of Part A.  If a pt does have a surgery or tumor biopsy , leftover tissue (or an additional core)  from this procedure may be used for molecular profiling. Clinical Assay(s): This testing will be performed in the CLIA-certified Molecular Diagnostics Service laboratory. Research Assay(s): This protocol will also be used as a platform to pilot the use of investigational &quot;next-generation&quot; profiling technologies .including whole exome sequencing, whole genome sequencing  RNA sequencing cell-free tumor DNA/RNA sequencing, &amp; others. To confirm the findings obtained on these assays using an orthogonal assay, additional sequencing such as Sanger,Sequenom, MiSeq or IMPACT testing may be utilized in either the CLIA or non-CLIA setting Part B: DTC Cohort Pts successfully registered to Part B of this study will be eligible for minimal risk collection &amp; research biopsies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pts with solid tumors</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical Germline Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Part C: Clinical Germline Analysis Participants who have donated a matched normal peripheral blood sample for comparison to somatic sequence will be offered the opportunity to have that germline DNA sample analyzed for the presence of deleterious or likely deleterious mutations in genes on the MSK-IMPACT panel that are known to be linked to inherited susceptibility or that are included on consensus lists of genes that should undergo secondary analysis (e.g. the &quot;ACMG list&quot;).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pts with solid tumors</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      tissue, blood, saliva or nail clippings
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with solid or hematologic cancers  who  may be and considered potential
        candidates for a therapeutic protocol will be recruited to Part A of this study.
        Enrollment to therapeutic clinical trials will not be contingent on enrollment in this
        protocol.

        Part B: Research Collection Cohort Patients potentially appropriate will be identified by
        their treating physician in each participating Disease Management Team.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Part A:

          -  Patients with solid or hematologic tumor.

          -  There is Sufficient archival tissue for molecular profiling a plan to obtain fresh
             tumor tissue as routine standard of care or part of a research biopsy from another
             therapeutic clinical trial and/or obtain from outside source.

        Part B:

          -  Patients successfully registered to Part A of (MSKCC IRB # 12-245)

          -  Prior written approval for patient consent obtained from Director of the Center fo
             Molecular Oncology, or a Principal/Co-Principal Investigator of MSKCC IRB # 12-245.

        Part C:

          -  Patient must be receiving ongoing care at MSK. Treatment at an MSK Alliance Site does
             not qualify.

          -  Patient must have successfully consented to Part A of this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unwilling or unable to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Hyman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Hyman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-4544</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Solit, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-2641</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Hyman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4544</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>David Solit, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-2641</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Hyman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 23, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 21, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tissue</keyword>
  <keyword>blood</keyword>
  <keyword>salvia</keyword>
  <keyword>buccal swab</keyword>
  <keyword>Genomic Profiling</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>hematologic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical Assay</keyword>
  <keyword>Research Assay</keyword>
  <keyword>12-245</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
