<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="76">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 08, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00084383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>J9988</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA088058</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA006973</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>JHOC-J9988</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00084383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vaccine Therapy Combined With Adjuvant Chemoradiotherapy in Treating Patients With Resected Stage I or Stage II Adenocarcinoma (Cancer) of the Pancreas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Safety and Efficacy Trial of Lethally Irradiated Allogeneic Pancreatic Tumor Cells Transfected With the GM-CSF Gene in Combination With Adjuvant Chemoradiotherapy for the Treatment of Adenocarcinoma of the Pancreas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Vaccines made from gene-modified pancreatic cancer cells may make the body build
      an immune response to kill tumor cells. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as fluorouracil,
      work in different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so they stop growing or die.
      Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to damage tumor cells. Giving vaccine therapy
      together with chemotherapy and radiation therapy after surgery may kill any remaining tumor
      cells.

      PURPOSE: This phase II trial is studying how well giving vaccine therapy together with
      adjuvant chemoradiotherapy works in treating patients with resected stage I or stage II
      adenocarcinoma (cancer) of the pancreas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  Determine overall and disease-free survival of patients with resected stage I or II
           adenocarcinoma of the pancreas treated with adjuvant chemoradiotherapy in combination
           with GVAX pancreatic cancer vaccine.

      Secondary

        -  Correlate specific in vivo parameters of immune response (post-vaccination delayed-type
           hypersensitivity reactions to autologous tumor, mesothelin-specific T-cell response,
           and the degree of local eosinophil, macrophage, and T-cell infiltration at the vaccine
           site) with clinical responses in patients treated with this regimen.

        -  Determine the toxic effects associated with intradermal injections of this vaccine in
           these patients.

      OUTLINE: This is an open-label study.

        -  Post surgery vaccination: Within 8-10 weeks after pancreaticoduodenectomy, patients
           receive GVAX pancreatic cancer vaccine intradermally (ID) on day 0.

        -  Adjuvant chemoradiotherapy: Within 16-28 days after the first vaccination, patients
           receive fluorouracil (5-FU) IV continuously for 3 weeks. Approximately 1-2 weeks after
           completion of 5-FU, patients receive chemoradiotherapy comprising radiotherapy daily
           and 5-FU IV continuously for 26-28 weeks. Approximately 3-5 weeks after completion of
           chemoradiotherapy, patients receive 5-FU IV continuously for 4 weeks. 5-FU repeats
           every 6 weeks for 2 courses.

        -  Post chemoradiotherapy vaccination: Within 4-8 weeks after the completion of
           chemoradiotherapy, patients receive GVAX pancreatic cancer vaccine ID on days 0, 28,
           56, and 196.

      Treatment continues in the absence of unacceptable toxicity.

      Patients are followed every 3 months for 1 year and then every 6 months thereafter.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 60 patients will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed for the duration of the study, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival in patients treated with adjuvant chemoradiotherapy in sequence with the irradiated allogeneic GM-CSF transfected pancreatic tumor cell lines. Overall survival is defined as time from surgery until death, regardless of cause.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants were followed for the duration of the study, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Disease-free Survival in Patients Treated With Adjuvant Chemoradiotherapy in Sequence With the Irradiated Allogeneic GM-CSF Transfected Pancreatic Tumor Cell Lines. DFS is defined as time from surgery until clinical evidence of disease (eg, CT scan) or death due to any cause.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To Further Identify and Characterize Toxicities Associated With Intradermal Injections of the Vaccine That Were Initially Reported in the Phase 1 Trial.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate the Association of Specific in Vivo Parameters of Immune Response With Clinical Responses in Patients Treated With Combination Chemoradiotherapy Together With the Irradiated Allogeneic GM-CSF Transfected Pancreatic Tumor Cell Lines.</measure>
    <time_frame>Continuous</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The specific immune parameters include: post-vaccination delayed type hypersensitivity reactions to autologous tumor and the degree of local eosinophil, macrophage, and T cell infiltration at the vaccine site, and mesothelin-specific T cell responses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GVAX pancreatic cancer vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5E8 vaccine cells. The first vaccination is administered 6-8 weeks after surgery. Four to eight weeks following the completion of the last cycle of adjuvant radiation and chemotherapy (chemo-radiation therapy is standard of care and not part of the protocol) eligible patients will receive three additional vaccinations at one month intervals. Patients who continue to remain disease-free will receive a fifth &quot;booster&quot; vaccination, six months following the fourth vaccination</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GVAX pancreatic cancer vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive vaccinations consisting of 5E8 vaccine cells. The first vaccination is administered 6-8 weeks after surgery. Four to eight weeks following the completion of the last cycle of adjuvant radiation and chemotherapy (chemo-radiation therapy is standard of care and not part of the protocol) eligible patients will receive three additional vaccinations at one month intervals. Patients who continue to remain disease-free will receive a fifth &quot;booster&quot; vaccination, six months following the fourth vaccination.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GVAX pancreatic cancer vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histologically confirmed invasive ductal adenocarcinoma of the head, neck, and
             uncinate process of the pancreas

               -  Mixed adenocarcinoma tumors allowed if the predominant invasive component of the
                  tumor is adenocarcinoma

               -  Stage I or II (clinical stage T1-3, N0-1, M0) disease

          -  Has undergone pancreaticoduodenectomy at the Johns Hopkins Hospital within the past
             8-10 weeks

               -  Completely resected (R0) or microscopic residual (R1) disease

          -  No diagnosis other than ductal adenocarcinoma, including any of the following:

               -  Adenosquamous

               -  Squamous cell

               -  Colloid

               -  Islet cell

               -  Non-invasive intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms

               -  Serous or mucinous cystadenoma or cystadenocarcinoma

               -  Carcinoid

               -  Small or large cell carcinoma

               -  Intraductal oncocytic papillary neoplasms

               -  Osteoclast-like giant cell tumors

               -  Acinar cell carcinoma

               -  Pancreatoblastoma

               -  Solid pseudopapillary tumors

               -  Undifferentiated small cell carcinoma

               -  Non-epithelial tumors (sarcoma, gastrointestinal stromal tumor, or lymphoma)

               -  Adenocarcinoma of the ampulla

               -  Adenocarcinoma of the distal bile duct

               -  Adenocarcinoma of the duodenum

          -  No recurrent disease

          -  No metastatic disease, including peritoneal implants or liver and/or lung involvement

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

        Age

          -  18 and over

        Performance status

          -  ECOG 0-1

        Life expectancy

          -  Not specified

        Hematopoietic

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;/= 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &gt;/= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;/= 10 g/dL

        Hepatic

          -  Bilirubin &lt;/= 2 mg/dL

          -  AST/ALT &lt;/= 2 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Alkaline phosphatase &lt;/= 5 times ULN

        Renal

          -  Creatinine &lt;/= 2 mg/dL

        Pulmonary

          -  No asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease requiring systemic corticosteroids

        Immunologic

          -  HIV negative

          -  No active infection

          -  No prior or concurrent autoimmune disease requiring treatment with systemic
             immunosuppressants, including any of the following:

               -  Inflammatory bowel disease

               -  Systemic vasculitis

               -  Scleroderma

               -  Psoriasis

               -  Multiple sclerosis

               -  Hemolytic anemia or immune thrombocytopenia

               -  Rheumatoid arthritis

               -  Systemic lupus erythematosus

               -  Sjogren's syndrome

               -  Sarcoidosis

          -  Negative results to viral delayed-type hypersensitivity serology testing if
             autologous tumor cells are available

        Other

          -  No postoperative complications (e.g., inability to take oral nutrition &gt;/= 1,500
             calories/day, ongoing requirement for long-term biliary stenting, or persistence of
             wound infection)

          -  No other malignancy within the past 5 years except nonmelanoma skin cancer

          -  No uncontrolled medical conditions that would preclude study participation

          -  No other major active medical or psychosocial problem that could be exacerbated by
             study treatment

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception during and for at least 4 weeks
             after study participation

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

        Biologic therapy

          -  More than 1 month since prior biologic therapy

          -  No other concurrent biologic therapy, immunotherapy, or gene therapy for pancreatic
             cancer

        Chemotherapy

          -  More than 1 month since prior chemotherapy

          -  No other concurrent chemotherapy for pancreatic cancer

        Endocrine therapy

          -  More than 28 days since prior systemic steroids

          -  No concurrent systemic corticosteroids

        Radiotherapy

          -  More than 1 month since prior radiotherapy

          -  No other concurrent radiotherapy for pancreatic cancer

        Surgery

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  Recovered from prior surgery

        Other

          -  More than 1 month since prior participation in an investigational new drug trial

          -  No other concurrent investigational therapy for pancreatic cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel A. Laheru, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21231</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/JHOC-J9988</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ? database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 17, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 10, 2004</firstreceived_date>
  <firstreceived_results_date>March 1, 2013</firstreceived_results_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stage I pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>duct cell adenocarcinoma of the pancreas</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results are available for this study                                           -->
</clinical_study>
