<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<article>
  <title>Risk of bladder cancer in patients with diabetes: a retrospective cohort study </title>
  <authors>
    <author name="Maria E Goossens"/>
    <author name="Maurice P Zeegers"/>
    <author name="Marloes T Bazelier"/>
    <author name="Marie L De Bruin"/>
    <author name="Frank Buntinx"/>
    <author name="Frank de Vries"/>
  </authors>
  <body>
    <p>&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt; The objective of this study was to examine the association between diabetes, and both urinary bladder cancer (UBC) risk and
                                    mortality.
                                 </p>
    <p>&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt; We conducted a retrospective cohort study using data from the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) linked to the
                                    Office of National Statistics (ONS). Patients diagnosed with diabetes mellitus type 1 or 2, or using antidiabetic drugs (ADDs),
                                    were compared to matched non-diabetic controls. Cox proportional hazards models were used to estimate the risk and mortality
                                    of UBC. We adjusted for age, sex, smoking status and body mass index.
                                 </p>
    <p>&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt; The cohort included 329&#8197;168 patients using ADD, and 307&#8197;315 controls with 1295 and 1071 patients, respectively, diagnosed
                                    as having UBC during follow-up. The adjusted HRs of UBC were 0.77 (95% CI 0.57 to 1.05) and 1.04 (95% CI 0.96 to 1.14) for
                                    type 1 and 2 diabetes, respectively. These results were similar if we restricted our analysis to an inception cohort. We noticed
                                    a small increased risk during the first year after diagnosis (HR=1.26 (95% CI 1.05 to 1.52)), which could be explained by
                                    detection bias. There was no influence of the severity of diabetes as measured by the glycated haemoglobin. Mortality of UBC
                                    was not increased for patients with either type 1 (HR=0.95 (95% CI 0.39 to 2.34)) or type 2 diabetes (HR=1.16 (95% CI 0.91
                                    to 1.46)).
                                 </p>
    <p>&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt; Neither the risk of UBC nor the mortality from UBC was increased in patients with type 1 and patients with type 2 diabetes
                                    in the CPRD data.
                                 </p>
    <p>The Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) is a large population-based cohort representative of the total UK population.</p>
    <p>Detailed longitudinal information on drug prescription is available within the CPRD, and 95% and 80% of patients with type
                                       1 and 2 diabetes, respectively, had received a formal diabetes diagnosis.
                                    </p>
    <p>Smoking status was available for all patients in our analysis.</p>
    <p>Detailed information about the cause of death is available for 44% of the patients by linking the patients to the Office of
                                       National Statistics (ONS) data.
                                    </p>
    <p>The effect of different antidiabetic drug medications is not considered in our analyses and this is a major limitation.</p>
    <p>The global 2013 estimate of diabetes mellitus prevalence among adults (aged 20&#8211;79&#8197;years) was 8.3%, affecting 382 million adults
                                 in the world and 6.6% in the UK.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-1" id="xref-ref-1-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; Between 2010 and 2030, the number of adults with diabetes in developing countries is expected to increase by 69%, and by
                                 20% in developed countries.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-2" id="xref-ref-2-1"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-3" id="xref-ref-3-1"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt; In 2012, more than 400&#8197;000 cases of urinary bladder cancer (UBC) occurred worldwide, making it the seventh most common type
                                 of cancer.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-4" id="xref-ref-4-1"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt; It is more frequent in men than in women, and age is now widely accepted as the greatest single risk factor for developing
                                 UBC. Cigarette smoking and specific occupational exposures, such as carcinogenic dyes for painters and some genetic polymorphisms,
                                 are the other main known causes of UBC.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-5" id="xref-ref-5-1"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt; Previous meta-analyses from cohort and case&#8211;control studies have shown an increased risk of UBC associated with type 2 diabetes
                                 with relative risks (RR) ranging from 1.11 (95% CI 1.00 to 1.23) to 1.32 (95% CI 1.18 to 1.49).&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-6" id="xref-ref-6-1"&gt;6&#8211;9&lt;/a&gt; There is also evidence for a positive association between type 2 diabetes and mortality from UBC (RR=1.33 (95% CI 1.14 to
                                 1.55).&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-7" id="xref-ref-7-1"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt; However, misclassification of type 1 and 2 diabetes was not excluded in these studies, because diagnostic codes were lacking
                                 and details about the diabetic history (duration, metabolic control) were not considered.
                              </p>
    <p>Two studies on type 1 diabetes reported an increased overall cancer incidence by 20%, while the mechanisms remain unclear.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-10" id="xref-ref-10-1"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-11" id="xref-ref-11-1"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt; The observed number of bladder cancer cases in these studies is very small, ranging from 4 to 27 cases.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-10" id="xref-ref-10-2"&gt;10&#8211;12&lt;/a&gt; The objective of this study was to examine the association between diabetes mellitus, and both UBC risk and mortality, taking
                                 into account diabetes duration, metabolic control as expressed by glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) and type of diabetes.
                              </p>
    <p>We conducted a retrospective cohort study using data from the UK Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) (January 1987&#8211;October
                                    2013) linked to the Office of National Statistics (ONS) (January 1998&#8211;January 2012). The CPRD comprises prospectively collected
                                    computerised medical records of over 10 million patients under the care of more than 600 general practitioners (GPs) in the
                                    UK. The Read classification is used to enter medical diagnoses and procedures, and prescriptions are recorded based on the
                                    UK &lt;em&gt;Prescription Pricing Authority Dictionary&lt;/em&gt;.
                                 </p>
    <p>The recorded information on diagnoses and drug use was validated, and proved to be of high quality.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-13" id="xref-ref-13-1"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt; The ONS provided data for the cause(s) of death and the exact date of death as recorded on death certificates by a registered
                                    medical practitioner attending to the patient during their last period.
                                 </p>
    <p>All patients with at least one prescription of antidiabetic drugs (ADDs) (oral antidiabetic drugs (NIADs) and/or insulin)
                                    and aged above 18&#8197;years during the period of valid CPRD data collection were included. Each ADD user was matched to one control
                                    patient by year of birth, sex and practice. Controls could have any disease as long as they were non-diabetic patients at
                                    baseline and during follow-up. The date of the first ADD prescription defined the index date and controls were assigned the
                                    same index date as their matched ADD user. All participants with missing data for smoking status, a history of any cancer
                                    prior to the index date, except non-melanoma skin cancer, or a diagnosis of gestational diabetes or secondary diabetes ever
                                    during follow-up were excluded. All control patients who used diabetes treatment or had ever been diagnosed with type 1 or
                                    2 diabetes ever during follow-up were excluded. All ADD users with diagnoses of type 1 and 2 diabetes were excluded as well,
                                    as were patients aged 30&#8197;years and older without a diagnosis of diabetes, who used insulin only at baseline. All study participants
                                    were followed up from the index date to either the end of data collection, the date of transfer of the patient out of the
                                    practice area, or the patient&#8217;s death.
                                 </p>
    <p>Patients with type 1 diabetes were defined as those patients with a formal diagnosis of type 1 diabetes (as recorded in CPRD)
                                    or younger than 30&#8197;years and using insulin only at index date. Patients with type 2 diabetes were all patients with a formal
                                    diagnosis of type 2 diabetes (as recorded in CPRD) or using an oral ADD at index date. The total period of follow-up for each
                                    patient (patients with diabetes and unexposed controls) was divided into fixed time periods of 90&#8197;days. Age was determined
                                    at the start of each interval. The classification of type 1 and 2 diabetes, as well as sex, smoking status and body mass index
                                    (BMI), was determined at baseline. Diabetes duration was assessed in a time-dependent manner by estimating the time since
                                    the date of the first ADD prescription (the index date). Diabetes control was assessed in a time-dependent manner using the
                                    most recent HbA1c record before the start of each time interval and within the previous year.
                                 </p>
    <p>The primary outcome was UBC, as defined by Read codes, and was assessed in the complete CPRD study population (January 1987&#8211;October
                                    2013). The secondary outcome was bladder cancer-related mortality as recorded on death certificates (International Classification
                                    of Diseases (ICD-10) categories C65, C67) and was assessed in the population eligible for linkage between CPRD and ONS data
                                    (44% of the participants). The period of follow-up was restricted to the time that ONS data were available (January 1998&#8211;January
                                    2012).
                                 </p>
    <p>The major covariates of interest included age, sex, smoking status and BMI. Smoking status was characterised at baseline as
                                    current, former or lifelong non-smoker.
                                 </p>
    <p>Analyses were conducted using Cox proportional hazards models with various subanalyses. As time scale we used time since first
                                    ADD use. We tested the proportional hazard assumption by comparing patients with diabetes to non-diabetes controls. The assumption
                                    was not violated. The first analysis compared the risk of UBC in ADD users with that in control patients to yield an estimate
                                    of the RR (as a HR) of UBC associated with ADD use. The calculations were adjusted for age, sex, smoking status and BMI. Results
                                    were stratified to type 1 and type 2 diabetes. A sensitivity analysis was performed excluding women with polycystic ovarian
                                    syndrome (PCOS). In a secondary analysis, risks were estimated for an inception cohort of ADD users using a 1-year lead-in
                                    time. The risk of UBC for patients with incident type 2 diabetic was further stratified by disease duration, sex and HbA1c.
                                    The risk of UBC mortality in ADD users compared with that of controls was assessed by Cox models as well and results were
                                    stratified by type of diabetes. All data management and statistical analyses were conducted using SAS V.9.1/9.2 software.
                                 </p>
    <p>This study was approved by the Medicines and Healthcare products Authorities&#8217; Independent Scientific Advisory Committee, protocol
                                    number 13_050R.
                                 </p>
    <p>After exclusion of all patients with a diagnosis of gestational diabetes (1983 and 154 for ADD users and controls, respectively),
                                 or secondary diabetes (485 and 70 for ADD users and controls, respectively), or cancer prior to index date (34&#8197;955 and 34&#8197;384
                                 for ADD users and controls, respectively) or missing data for smoking status during follow-up (13&#8197;416 and 27&#8197;558 for ADD users
                                 and controls, respectively), the study population consisted of 329&#8197;168 patients with diabetes of whom 30&#8197;823 (9.4%) and 298&#8197;345
                                 (90.6%) had type 1 and 2 diabetes, respectively, and 307&#8197;315 controls. Patients diagnosed with type 1 and 2 diabetes at baseline
                                 (7614) and patients without diagnosis, using insulin only at baseline and 30&#8197;years or older (10&#8197;178), were not included in
                                 our analysis.
                              </p>
    <p>&lt;a class="xref-table" href="#T1" id="xref-table-wrap-1-1"&gt;Table&#160;1&lt;/a&gt; shows baseline characteristics. The mean age at index date was 58&#8197;years. Forty-six per cent of the patients with diabetes
                                 had a BMI of 30 or above in contrast with 30% of the control participants.
                              </p>
    <p>Baseline characteristics of antidiabetic drug (ADD) users and non-diabetic controls</p>
    <p>During nearly 6&#8197;years of follow-up, 1071 patients of the control group and 1295 of the ADD users were diagnosed with bladder
                                 cancer. Patients with type 1 diabetes had no significantly lower risk of UBC (HR=0.77 (95% CI 0.57 to 1.05)) than patients
                                 with type 2 diabetes (HR=1.04 (95% CI 0.96 to 1.14)) based on a Wald test (p=0.054). The results for incident ADD users were
                                 similar (&lt;a class="xref-table" href="#T2" id="xref-table-wrap-2-1"&gt;table 2&lt;/a&gt;).
                              </p>
    <p>Risk of bladder cancer in antidiabetic drug (ADD) users compared with controls, by type of diabetes and in incident ADD users</p>
    <p>For patients with incident type 2 diabetes, we noticed an increased risk of UBC (HR=1.26 (95% CI 1.05 to 1.52)) during the
                                 first year after the first ADD prescription, compared to controls, which disappeared in subsequent years (&lt;a class="xref-table" href="#T3" id="xref-table-wrap-3-1"&gt;table 3&lt;/a&gt;). Sixty per cent of the bladder cancers developed during the first 5&#8197;years after diabetes onset. There was no difference
                                 in UBC risk between male and female patients with type 2 diabetes (HR=1.11 (95% CI 0.98 to 1.25) and 1.01 (95% CI 0.79 to
                                 1.29), respectively). In patients with type 2 diabetes, there was no influence of HbA1c as an indicator of diabetes severity
                                 on UBC risk (&lt;a class="xref-table" href="#T4" id="xref-table-wrap-4-1"&gt;table 4&lt;/a&gt;). UBC-related mortality was neither increased in patients with type 1 diabetes (HR=0.79 (95% CI 0.32 to 1.94)) nor in patients
                                 with type 2 diabetes, compared to controls (HR=1.05 (95% CI 0.83 to 1.33)) (&lt;a class="xref-table" href="#T5" id="xref-table-wrap-5-1"&gt;table 5&lt;/a&gt;).
                              </p>
    <p>Risk of bladder cancer in incident patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus compared with controls, by duration of disease and
                                       sex
                                    </p>
    <p>Risk of urinary bladder cancer in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus by HbA1c level at most recent measurement</p>
    <p>Risk of urinary bladder cancer (UBC) mortality in antidiabetic drug (ADD) users compared with controls, by type of diabetes
                                       mellitus
                                    </p>
    <p>We could not detect a significantly increased risk of UBC nor of increased mortality due to UBC in patients with type 1 and
                                 2 diabetes compared to controls even if we reduced our cohort to incident ADD users. However, we noticed an increased risk
                                 of UBC in patients with type 2 diabetes during the first year after diagnosis. Diabetes control, as expressed by HbA1c, had
                                 no influence on the UBC risk in patients with type 2 diabetes.
                              </p>
    <p>Previous meta-analyses reported an increased risk.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-6" id="xref-ref-6-2"&gt;6&#8211;9&lt;/a&gt; Even when these meta-analyses&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-6" id="xref-ref-6-3"&gt;6&#8211;8&lt;/a&gt; were restricted to studies that adjusted for smoking, there was still an increased RR ranging from 1.32 (95% CI 1.18 to 1.49)
                                 to 1.48 (95% CI 1.25 to 1.77), comparable to our RR for type 2 diabetes. On the other hand, in several studies, diabetes ascertainment
                                 was based on self-reporting.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-8" id="xref-ref-8-1"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt; Those studies had an RR of 1.34 (95% CI 1.11 to 1.62). The increased risk of UBC in patients with diabetes decreased and
                                 significance disappeared when diabetes was asserted by other methods (RR=1.11 (95% CI 0.95 to 1.31)). Furthermore, not all
                                 studies distinguished between diabetes type 1 and 2. Most of the studies excluded type 1 diabetes as a diagnosis of diabetes
                                 before 30&#8197;years of age.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-7" id="xref-ref-7-2"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-8" id="xref-ref-8-2"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt; Subgroup analysis of studies restricted to Europe did not show an increased risk of UBC in patients with type 2 diabetes.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-6" id="xref-ref-6-4"&gt;6&#8211;8&lt;/a&gt; Hence, our results are in line with those of European studies.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-12" id="xref-ref-12-1"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-14" id="xref-ref-14-1"&gt;14&#8211;21&lt;/a&gt; It is not clear why there is a difference between European studies and those of other regions.
                              </p>
    <p>We did not find an increased risk of bladder cancer in diabetes type 1, which is in line with the results found in Sweden&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-10" id="xref-ref-10-3"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-11" id="xref-ref-11-2"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt; and in the UK.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-12" id="xref-ref-12-2"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;</p>
    <p>An increased risk of UBC during the first year after diabetes diagnosis was found in several other studies.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-20" id="xref-ref-20-1"&gt;20&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-22" id="xref-ref-22-1"&gt;22&#8211;24&lt;/a&gt; Likewise, for colorectal, lung, breast, liver, cervical, endometrial, ovarian, pancreatic and prostate cancers, a significantly
                                 increased risk was found within the months following diabetes onset.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-10" id="xref-ref-10-4"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-25" id="xref-ref-25-1"&gt;25&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-26" id="xref-ref-26-1"&gt;26&lt;/a&gt; This most likely indicates the presence of a detection bias, in the sense that the diagnosis of diabetes leads to increased
                                 medical attention, and thus to earlier detection of any present but undiagnosed cancer. This phenomenon has also been observed
                                 immediately after the diagnosis of prostate cancer. The incidence of UBC was 18 times higher in patients with prostate cancer
                                 due to diagnostic bias.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-27" id="xref-ref-27-1"&gt;27&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-28" id="xref-ref-28-1"&gt;28&lt;/a&gt; On the other hand, in contrast with some other studies, we could not confirm the hypothesis that fewer physician visits in
                                 the year before diabetes diagnosis increases the risk of bladder cancer diagnosis in contrast with some other studies.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-24" id="xref-ref-24-1"&gt;24&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-26" id="xref-ref-26-2"&gt;26&lt;/a&gt; Apart from the increased risk of UBC during the first year of diabetes diagnosis, possibly due to detection bias, we did
                                 not find an association between diabetes duration and developing bladder cancer. Seeing that nearly 50% of the patients had
                                 a follow-up of more than 5&#8197;years and only 40% of the bladder cancers were diagnosed after these 5&#8197;years, while only 10% was
                                 diagnosed after 10&#8197;years, we can conclude that having diabetes for more than 5&#8197;years did not alter the risk of UBC.
                              </p>
    <p>Our finding of no association between HbA1c and cancer risk is consistent with the results of a recent meta-analysis of major
                                 randomised controlled trials.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-29" id="xref-ref-29-1"&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;</p>
    <p>The strength of this study was that the CPRD is a large population-based cohort, representative of the total UK population.
                                 Type 2 diabetes accounts for 85% to 95% of all diabetes in high-income countries.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-1" id="xref-ref-1-2"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; In the UK, 10% of the people with diabetes have type 1,&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-30" id="xref-ref-30-1"&gt;30&lt;/a&gt; which was confirmed in our analysis (9.4%). We had detailed longitudinal information on drug prescription, and 95% and 80%
                                 of the patients with type 1 and 2 diabetes, respectively, had received a formal diabetes diagnosis. Patients with type 1 and
                                 2 diabetes at baseline, and patients without diagnosis, using insulin only at baseline and 30&#8197;years or older, were excluded
                                 from our analysis. Consulting rates for diabetes in the CPRD have been compared with equivalent data from the fourth National
                                 Morbidity Survey in General Practice, confirming the validity of the morbidity data in the CPRD.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-31" id="xref-ref-31-1"&gt;31&lt;/a&gt; Furthermore, since 2004, GPs have been stimulated to provide &#8216;quality care&#8217; by the Quality and Outcomes Framework (QOF).
                                 The UK has a National Service Framework for Diabetes (NSF).&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-32" id="xref-ref-32-1"&gt;32&lt;/a&gt; Guidelines to be followed by the GPs are outlined in the guideline for type 1&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-33" id="xref-ref-33-1"&gt;33&lt;/a&gt; and 2 diabetes&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-34" id="xref-ref-34-1"&gt;34&lt;/a&gt; of the National Institute of Health and Care Excellence (NICE). For diagnosis, the NICE guideline refers to the International
                                 Diabetes Federation (IDF) Diabetes Atlas.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-1" id="xref-ref-1-3"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; Diagnosis of diabetes is directly linked with prescription of ADD whereas Impaired Glucose Tolerance (IGT) is referred to
                                 as people whose blood glucose levels are high but not as high as those in people with diabetes. Our cohort was restricted
                                 to those patients receiving ADD. Furthermore, we had HbA1c values for 1251 of the 1295 patients with bladder cancer. So, 96%
                                 of the patients have additional proof of being diabetic.
                              </p>
    <p>Metformin can also be used to treat obesity or PCOS. We have no means to test the possible effect of metformin prescribed
                                 for obesity, although the clinical impression exists that such treatments tend to be relatively short. In our cohort, 12&#8197;841
                                 women were diagnosed with PCOS. None of them developed UBC. A sensitivity analysis, excluding those PCOS women, showed exactly
                                 the same HRs. Additionally, we have information on the smoking status of all patients who were included in our analysis, which
                                 is essential given that smoking is one of the major risk factors for bladder cancer.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-5" id="xref-ref-5-2"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt; The link with the ONS data allowed us to have detailed information about the cause of death for 44% of patients.
                              </p>
    <p>The fact that the effect of different antidiabetic drug medications was not considered in our analyses is a major limitation.
                                 We are aware of the fact that metformin can have a protective effect on cancer&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-3" id="xref-ref-3-2"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="xref-sep"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-35" id="xref-ref-35-1"&gt;35&lt;/a&gt; and that pioglitazone could be associated with an increased risk of bladder cancer.&lt;a class="xref-bibr" href="#ref-36" id="xref-ref-36-1"&gt;36&#8211;40&lt;/a&gt; This was, however, beyond the scope of this study.
                              </p>
    <p>With this study, and against the background of all previous research, the likelihood of a clinically relevant association
                                 between diabetes and UBC risk has become very limited. The influence of antidiabetic treatment on bladder cancer risk, however,
                                 is still contradictable and requires further study in the future.
                              </p>
    <p>Neither the risk of UBC nor the mortality from UBC was observed to be increased in patients with type 1 or type 2 diabetes
                                 in the CPRD data. Our results are in line with those of previous European studies.
                              </p>
    <p>&lt;span class="fn-label"&gt;Contributors&lt;/span&gt; MEG wrote the manuscript and researched data. MTB performed the statistical analysis and reviewed the manuscript. FB and
                                       MPZ reviewed/edited the manuscript. FdV and MLDB provided the data and reviewed/edited the manuscript.
                                    </p>
    <p>&lt;span class="fn-label"&gt;Funding&lt;/span&gt; The research leading to the results of this study received funding from the European Community's Seventh Framework Programme
                                       (FP-7) under grant agreement number 282526, the CARING project. The funding source had no role in study design, data collection,
                                       data analysis, data interpretation or writing of the report.
                                    </p>
    <p>&lt;span class="fn-label"&gt;Competing interests&lt;/span&gt; The Department of Pharmacoepidemiology and Clinical Pharmacology employing authors MTB and FdV received unrestricted funding
                                       for pharmacoepidemiological research from GlaxoSmithKline, Novo Nordisk, the private&#8211;public-funded Top Institute Pharma (&lt;a href="http://www.tipharma.nl"&gt;http://www.tipharma.nl&lt;/a&gt;; includes co-funding from universities, government and industry), the Dutch Medicines Evaluation Board and the Dutch Ministry
                                       of Health. The GPRD is owned by the UK Department of Health and operates within the Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory
                                       Agency (MHRA). GPRD is funded by the MHRA, Medical Research Council, various universities, contract research organisations
                                       and pharmaceutical companies. MLDB is employed by Utrecht University as a senior researcher conducting research in collaboration
                                       with the WHO Collaborating Centre for pharmaceutical policy and regulation. This Centre receives no direct funding or donations
                                       from private parties, including the pharma industry. Research funding from public-private partnerships, for example, IMI and
                                       TI Pharma (&lt;a href="http://www.tipharma.nl"&gt;http://www.tipharma.nl&lt;/a&gt;), is accepted under the condition that no company-specific product or company related study is conducted. The Centre has
                                       received unrestricted research funding from public sources, for example, Netherlands Organization for Health Research and
                                       Development (ZonMW), the Dutch Health Care Insurance Board (CVZ), EU 7th Framework Program (FP7), Dutch Medicines Evaluation
                                       Board (MEB) and Dutch Ministry of Health.
                                    </p>
    <p>&lt;span class="fn-label"&gt;Ethics approval&lt;/span&gt; Medicines and Healthcare products Authorities&#8217; Independent Scientific Advisory Committee.
                                    </p>
    <p>&lt;span class="fn-label"&gt;Provenance and peer review&lt;/span&gt; Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.
                                    </p>
    <p>&lt;span class="fn-label"&gt;Data sharing statement&lt;/span&gt; CPRD data are available under license with the Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory Agency (MHRA) in London, UK.
                                       The datasets that have been used for this project have been licensed by the MHRA. Access to datasets that have been used for
                                       this study are available for audit purposes only, conditional on permission by the MHRA.
                                    </p>
    <p>This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0)
                                 license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative
                                 works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" rel="license"&gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&lt;/a&gt;</p>
  </body>
  <references>
    <reference collaboration="International Diabetes Federation" source="IDF diabetes atlas" edition="6th edn" publ-location="Brussels, Belgium" publ-name="International Diabetes Federation" publ-date="2013" link="http://www.idf.org/diabetesatlas"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Shaw,JE" name-author-2="Sicree,RA" name-author-3="Zimmet,PZ" jnl-abbrev="Diabetes Res Clin Pract" publ-date="2010" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.diabres.2009.10.007"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Ngwana,G" name-author-2="Aerts,M" name-author-3="Truyers,C" jnl-abbrev="Diabetes Res Clin Pract" publ-date="2012" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.diabres.2012.02.002"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Ferlay,J" name-author-2="Soerjomataram,I" name-author-3="Ervik,M" link="http://globocan.iarc.fr"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Goossens,ME" name-author-2="Buntinx,F" name-author-3="Zeegers,MP" source="The Oxford textbook of surgery" publ-name="Oxford University Press (OUP)" publ-date="2015"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Larsson,SC" name-author-2="Orsini,N" name-author-3="Brismar,K" jnl-abbrev="Diabetologia" publ-date="2006" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00125-006-0468-0"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Zhu,Z" name-author-2="Zhang,X" name-author-3="Shen,Z" jnl-abbrev="PLoS ONE" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0056662"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Xu,X" name-author-2="Wu,J" name-author-3="Mao,Y" jnl-abbrev="PLoS ONE" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0058079"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Starup-Linde,J" name-author-2="Karlstad,O" name-author-3="Eriksen,SA" jnl-abbrev="Curr Drug Saf" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.2174/15748863113086660071"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Shu,X" name-author-2="Ji,J" name-author-3="Li,X" jnl-abbrev="Diabet Med" publ-date="2010" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1464-5491.2010.03011.x"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Zendehdel,K" name-author-2="Nyren,O" name-author-3="Ostenson,CG" jnl-abbrev="J Natl Cancer Inst" publ-date="2003" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jnci/djg105"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Swerdlow,AJ" name-author-2="Laing,SP" name-author-3="Qiao,Z" jnl-abbrev="Br J Cancer" publ-date="2005" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/sj.bjc.6602611"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Herrett,E" name-author-2="Thomas,SL" name-author-3="Schoonen,WM" jnl-abbrev="Br J Clin Pharmacol" publ-date="2010" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2125.2009.03537.x"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Adami,HO" name-author-2="McLaughlin,J" name-author-3="Ekbom,A" jnl-abbrev="Cancer Causes Control" publ-date="1991" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00051670"/>
    <reference name-author-1="La Vecchia,C" name-author-2="Negri,E" name-author-3="Franceschi,S" jnl-abbrev="Br J Cancer" publ-date="1994" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/bjc.1994.427"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Wideroff,L" name-author-2="Gridley,G" name-author-3="Mellemkjaer,L" jnl-abbrev="J Natl Cancer Inst" publ-date="1997" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jnci/89.18.1360"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Ng,Y" name-author-2="Husain,I" name-author-3="Waterfall,N" jnl-abbrev="Pathol Oncol Res" publ-date="2003" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF03033711"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Verlato,G" name-author-2="Drane,JW" name-author-3="Aldrich,TE" jnl-abbrev="Diabetes Nutr Metab" publ-date="2003"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Larsson,SC" name-author-2="Andersson,SO" name-author-3="Johansson,JE" jnl-abbrev="Eur J Cancer" publ-date="2008" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ejca.2008.07.012"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Ogunleye,AA" name-author-2="Ogston,SA" name-author-3="Morris,AD" jnl-abbrev="Br J Cancer" publ-date="2009" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/sj.bjc.6605240"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Attner,B" name-author-2="Landin-Olsson,M" name-author-3="Lithman,T" jnl-abbrev="Cancer Causes Control" publ-date="2012" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10552-012-9946-5"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Hemminki,K" name-author-2="Li,X" name-author-3="Sundquist,J" jnl-abbrev="Oncologist" publ-date="2010" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1634/theoncologist.2009-0300"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Atchison,EA" name-author-2="Gridley,G" name-author-3="Carreon,JD" jnl-abbrev="Int J Cancer" publ-date="2011" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ijc.25362"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Colmers,IN" name-author-2="Majumdar,SR" name-author-3="Yasui,Y" jnl-abbrev="Diabetes Care" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/dc13-0045"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Carstensen,B" name-author-2="Witte,DR" name-author-3="Friis,S" jnl-abbrev="Diabetologia" publ-date="2012" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00125-011-2381-4"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Johnson,JA" name-author-2="Bowker,SL" name-author-3="Richardson,K" jnl-abbrev="Diabetologia" publ-date="2011" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00125-011-2242-1"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Kellen,E" name-author-2="Zeegers,MP" name-author-3="Dirx,M" jnl-abbrev="Eur J Cancer" publ-date="2007" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ejca.2007.04.011"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Kellen,E" name-author-2="Zeegers,MP" name-author-3="Joniau,S" jnl-abbrev="Future Oncol" publ-date="2007" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.2217/14796694.3.5.515"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Johnson,JA" name-author-2="Bowker,SL" jnl-abbrev="Diabetologia" publ-date="2011" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00125-010-1933-3"/>
    <reference publ-date="2012"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Hollowell,J" jnl-abbrev="Popul Trends" publ-date="1997"/>
    <reference publ-date="2001"/>
    <reference collaboration="Type 1 diabetes|Guidance and guidelines|NICE" publ-date="2004" link="http://wwwniceorguk/guidance/cg15"/>
    <reference collaboration="Type 2 diabetes|Guidance and guidelines|NICE" publ-date="2009" link="http://wwwniceorguk/guidance/cg87"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Peeters,PJ" name-author-2="Bazelier,MT" name-author-3="Vestergaard,P" jnl-abbrev="Curr Drug Saf" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.2174/15680266113136660069"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Colmers,IN" name-author-2="Bowker,SL" name-author-3="Majumdar,SR" jnl-abbrev="CMAJ" publ-date="2012" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.112102"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Ferwana,M" name-author-2="Firwana,B" name-author-3="Hasan,R" jnl-abbrev="Diabet Med" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/dme.12144"/>
    <reference name-author-1="de Vries,F" name-author-2="Zeegers,MP" name-author-3="Knapen,LM" jnl-abbrev="Oncologist" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1634/theoncologist.2013-0087"/>
    <reference name-author-1="de Vries,F" name-author-2="Goossens,ME" name-author-3="Zeegers,MP" jnl-abbrev="Br J Clin Pharmacol" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/bcp.12145"/>
    <reference name-author-1="Bazelier,MT" name-author-2="de Vries,F" name-author-3="Vestergaard,P" jnl-abbrev="Curr Drug Saf" publ-date="2013" link="http://dx.doi.org/10.2174/15748863113086660069"/>
  </references>
</article>
